<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jingtao Lai on Jingtao Lai</title>
    <link>https://laijingtao.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Jingtao Lai on Jingtao Lai</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Jingtao Lai</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>paramparser</title>
      <link>https://laijingtao.github.io/code/paramparser/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2018 14:25:25 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://laijingtao.github.io/code/paramparser/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/laijingtao/paramparser&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Get source code from Github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>pypismplot</title>
      <link>https://laijingtao.github.io/code/pypismplot/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jan 2018 14:49:08 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://laijingtao.github.io/code/pypismplot/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/laijingtao/pypismplot&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Get source code from Github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plot PISM data using matplotlib and netcdf4-python&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Glacial erosion in orogenic belts</title>
      <link>https://laijingtao.github.io/project/glacial_erosion/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jan 2018 14:14:29 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://laijingtao.github.io/project/glacial_erosion/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relationship between late Cenozoic cooling and the dynamics of mountain building has been in debate for decades, and glacial erosion is a critical component that links climate to tectonic deformation. Glaciers may limit the height of mountain ranges through an efficient denudation mechanism known as “glacial buzzsaw”. This theory is supported by a correlation between the equilibrium line altitudes (ELA) and maximum height of mountain ranges. However, the correlation between ELA and mountain heights breaks down in high-latitude regions, where mountain peaks attain elevations above the ELA of Last Glacial Maximum (LGM) and erosion is slower than mid-latitude regions. The specific mechanisms responsible for such observations are in debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One hypothesis is that toward high-latitude region, glaciers are more frequently frozen to the bed and these cold-based glaciers will protect topography from erosion. Glaciers erode bedrock primarily by abrasion and quarrying. Although the detailed physical mechanism of glacial erosion still remains unclear,  most landscape evolution models assume a power law that relates glacial erosion rate to either sliding velocity or flux of glaciers. Cold-based glaciers have lower sliding velocity and flux, therefore they are less erosive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This research aims to test this hypothesis using numerical models. We will quantify the impact of climate on glacier dynamics and estimate the glacial erosion rates in orogenic belts. We will investigate the spatial pattern of glacial erosion rates under different climatic conditions. Furthermore, we will investigate how bedrock topography responds to different patterns of glacial erosion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;method&#34;&gt;Method&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I conduct a series of numerical experiments to simulate the glaciation in a steady-state mountain belt using &lt;a href=&#34;http://pism-docs.org/wiki/doku.php?id=home&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Parallel Ice Sheet Model (PISM)&lt;/a&gt;. The bedrock topography is a synthetic fluvial landscape in steady state, representing typical pre-glaciation landscapes. The experiments cover a range of various climatic conditions represented by different values of mean annual sea-level temperature and mean annual precipitation. The erosion rate is estimated by a linear erosion law that the erosion rate is proportional to the basal sliding velocity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to learn more about this research, &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:jlai11@illinois.edu&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;contact me&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Landlab</title>
      <link>https://laijingtao.github.io/code/landlab/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jan 2018 15:26:24 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://laijingtao.github.io/code/landlab/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/laijingtao/landlab&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Get source code from Github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Post-glacial landscape evolution</title>
      <link>https://laijingtao.github.io/project/postglacial/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jan 2018 14:01:16 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://laijingtao.github.io/project/postglacial/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Landscapes of the US Midwest were repeatedly affected by the southernmost portions of the Laurentide Ice Sheet during the Quaternary. Over much of the Midwest, depositional glacial processes diminished pre-glacial relief by filling valleys and left constructional landforms including low-relief till plains and high relief moraines. As the ice retreated, meltwater collected in subglacial or proglacial lakes leaving fine-grained, sorted sediment in the form of glacial lake plains. Glacial lakes episodically drained in outburst floods, carving deep valleys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, meltwater valleys did not provide a landscape-wide integrated drainage network. Instead, a significant fraction of the area of low-relief till plains and glacial lake plains was occupied by closed depressions and remained unconnected to external drainage networks. This area is referred to by hydrologists as non-contributing area (NCA) because it does not typically contribute surface runoff to stream networks. NCA becomes integrated into external drainage networks over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;hypothesis&#34;&gt;Hypothesis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We propose that this integration could occur via at least two different paths:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;through capture of NCA as channel heads propagate into the upland or,&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;through erosion of a channel along a flow path that, perhaps intermittently, connects NCA to the external drainage network.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We refer the two cases as &lt;strong&gt;“disconnected”&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;“connected”&lt;/strong&gt; since the crucial difference between them is the hydrological connection of the upland to external drainage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;method&#34;&gt;Method&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We investigate the difference in morphology and rate of growth of channel networks in low relief landscapes under disconnected and connected drainage regimes using numerical simulations of fluvial and hillslope processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We use the &lt;a href=&#34;http://landlab.github.io&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Landlab&lt;/a&gt; model platform to simulate the evolution of post-glacial landscapes, starting from a flat low-relief surface. The surface evolves via detachment-limited fluvial incision and hillslope diffusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The model is coupled with a new flow routing algorithm that represents upland connection by spillover of water from closed depressions. The modified version of Landlab is &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/laijingtao/landlab&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;findings&#34;&gt;Findings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The growth of channel network is faster in the connected case than in the disconnected case.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The channel network in the connected case has longer and more sinuous channels than the disconnected case.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To accomplish the same degree of integration, the connected case removes less sediment than the disconnected case.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Holding the volumes of water constant shows that the disconnected case is more efficient than the connected case at eroding for limited volumes of accumulated discharge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I presented this research in AGU 2017 Fall Meeting. A manuscript has been submitted to &lt;em&gt;Journal of Geophysical Research: Earth Surface&lt;/em&gt;. If you want to learn more about this research, &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:jlai11@illinois.edu&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;contact me&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello World</title>
      <link>https://laijingtao.github.io/post/hello_world/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2018 21:51:22 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://laijingtao.github.io/post/hello_world/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;hello-world&#34;&gt;Hello World!&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is my first post. I&amp;rsquo;m learning how to manage it with &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some useful links:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/hosting-and-deployment/hosting-on-github/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Host a website created by Hugo on Github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/managing-content/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Managing content&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Writing content&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-Jingtao&lt;br /&gt;
Jan 17 2018&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
