<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>landscape-evolution on Jingtao Lai</title>
    <link>https://laijingtao.github.io/tags/landscape-evolution/</link>
    <description>Recent content in landscape-evolution on Jingtao Lai</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Jingtao Lai</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 07 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://laijingtao.github.io/tags/landscape-evolution/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Climatic controls on glacial erosion – insights from numerical glacial landscape evolution modeling</title>
      <link>https://laijingtao.github.io/publication/lai-gsa-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://laijingtao.github.io/publication/lai-gsa-2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeled post-glacial landscape evolution at the southern margin of the Laurentide Ice Sheet: hydrological connection of uplands controls the pace and style of fluvial network expansion</title>
      <link>https://laijingtao.github.io/publication/lai-jgr-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://laijingtao.github.io/publication/lai-jgr-2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spatial patterns of glacial erosion in mountains</title>
      <link>https://laijingtao.github.io/project/glacial_erosion/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jan 2018 14:14:29 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://laijingtao.github.io/project/glacial_erosion/</guid>
      <description>Background The relationship between late Cenozoic cooling and the dynamics of mountain building has been in debate for decades, and glacial erosion is a critical component that links climate to tectonic deformation. Glaciers may limit the height of mountain ranges through an efficient denudation mechanism known as “glacial buzzsaw”. This theory is supported by a correlation between the equilibrium line altitudes (ELA) and maximum height of mountain ranges. However, the correlation between ELA and mountain heights breaks down in high-latitude regions, where mountain peaks attain elevations above the ELA of Last Glacial Maximum (LGM) and erosion is slower than mid-latitude regions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Post-glacial landscape evolution</title>
      <link>https://laijingtao.github.io/project/postglacial/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jan 2018 14:01:16 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://laijingtao.github.io/project/postglacial/</guid>
      <description>Background Landscapes of the US Midwest were repeatedly affected by the southernmost portions of the Laurentide Ice Sheet during the Quaternary. Over much of the Midwest, depositional glacial processes diminished pre-glacial relief by filling valleys and left constructional landforms including low-relief till plains and high relief moraines. As the ice retreated, meltwater collected in subglacial or proglacial lakes leaving fine-grained, sorted sediment in the form of glacial lake plains. Glacial lakes episodically drained in outburst floods, carving deep valleys.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeled post-glacial landscape evolution at the southern margin of the Laurentide Ice Sheet: hydrological connection of uplands controls the pace and style of fluvial network expansion</title>
      <link>https://laijingtao.github.io/publication/lai-agu-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Dec 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://laijingtao.github.io/publication/lai-agu-2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Numerical modeling of the evolution of fluvial networks on glaciated landscapes</title>
      <link>https://laijingtao.github.io/publication/lai-agu-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://laijingtao.github.io/publication/lai-agu-2016/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>