<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Landscape-evolution on Jingtao Lai</title>
    <link>https://laijingtao.github.io/tags/landscape-evolution/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Landscape-evolution on Jingtao Lai</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Jingtao Lai</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Dec 2018 00:00:00 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://laijingtao.github.io/tags/landscape-evolution/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A comparison of basal sliding and erosion in numerical glacial landscape evolution models using two different sliding laws</title>
      <link>https://laijingtao.github.io/publication/lai-agu-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Dec 2018 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://laijingtao.github.io/publication/lai-agu-2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Climatic controls on glacial erosion – insights from numerical glacial landscape evolution modeling</title>
      <link>https://laijingtao.github.io/publication/lai-gsa-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://laijingtao.github.io/publication/lai-gsa-2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeled post-glacial landscape evolution at the southern margin of the Laurentide Ice Sheet: hydrological connection of uplands controls the pace and style of fluvial network expansion</title>
      <link>https://laijingtao.github.io/publication/lai-jgr-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://laijingtao.github.io/publication/lai-jgr-2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spatial patterns of glacial erosion in mountains</title>
      <link>https://laijingtao.github.io/project/glacial_erosion/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jan 2018 14:14:29 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://laijingtao.github.io/project/glacial_erosion/</guid>
      <description>Climate plays a significant role in controlling the evolution of alpine landscapes by influencing the rate and pattern of alpine glacier erosion. The equilibrium line altitude (ELA) is a common way to collapse climate into a single variable. The ELA is an integration of various factors controlling glacial mass balance and the position of the ELA is largely controlled by local temperature and snowfall rates. The location of the most rapid erosion is suggested to coincide with the intersection of the ELA and topography because the efficiency of glacial erosion is often assumed to be highest where the ice flux is at the maximum.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Post-glacial landscape evolution</title>
      <link>https://laijingtao.github.io/project/postglacial/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jan 2018 14:01:16 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://laijingtao.github.io/project/postglacial/</guid>
      <description>Background Landscapes of the US Midwest were repeatedly affected by the southernmost portions of the Laurentide Ice Sheet during the Quaternary. Over much of the Midwest, depositional glacial processes diminished pre-glacial relief by filling valleys and left constructional landforms including low-relief till plains and high relief moraines. As the ice retreated, meltwater collected in subglacial or proglacial lakes leaving fine-grained, sorted sediment in the form of glacial lake plains. Glacial lakes episodically drained in outburst floods, carving deep valleys.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeled post-glacial landscape evolution at the southern margin of the Laurentide Ice Sheet: hydrological connection of uplands controls the pace and style of fluvial network expansion</title>
      <link>https://laijingtao.github.io/publication/lai-agu-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Dec 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://laijingtao.github.io/publication/lai-agu-2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Numerical modeling of the evolution of fluvial networks on glaciated landscapes</title>
      <link>https://laijingtao.github.io/publication/lai-agu-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://laijingtao.github.io/publication/lai-agu-2016/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>